<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2017 OpenPOWER Foundation
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  
-->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="sec_floatingpoint_exceptions">
  <title>Floating Point Exceptions</title>
  
  <para>Nominally both ISAs support the IEEE-754 specifications, but there are 
  some subtle differences. Both architectures define a status and control register 
  to record exceptions and enable / disable floating point exceptions for program 
  interrupt or default action. Intel has a MXCSR and PowerISA has a FPSCR which 
  basically do the same thing but with different bit layout. </para>

  <para>Intel provides <literal>_mm_setcsr</literal> / <literal>_mm_getcsr</literal> 
  intrinsic functions to allow direct access to the MXCSR. 
  This might have been useful in the early days before the OS run-times were 
  updated to manage the MXCSR via the  POSIX APIs. Today this would be 
  highly discouraged with a strong preference to use the POSIX APIs 
  (<literal>feclearexceptflag</literal>, 
  <literal>fegetexceptflag</literal>, 
  <literal>fesetexceptflag</literal>, ...) instead.</para>

  <para>If we implement <literal>_mm_setcsr</literal> / 
  <literal>_mm_getcs</literal> at all, we should simply 
  redirect the implementation to use the POSIX APIs from 
  <literal>&lt;fenv.h&gt;</literal>. But it 
  might be simpler just to replace these intrinsics with macros that generate 
  #error.</para>

  <para>The Intel MXCSR does have some non- (POSIX/IEEE754) standard quirks: 
  The Flush-To-Zero and Denormals-Are-Zeros flags. This simplifies the hardware 
  response to what should be a rare condition (underflows where the result can 
  not be represented in the exponent range and precision of the format) by simply 
  returning a signed 0.0 value. The intrinsic header implementation does provide 
  constant masks for <literal>_MM_DENORMALS_ZERO_ON</literal> 
  (<literal>&lt;pmmintrin.h&gt;</literal>) and 
  <literal>_MM_FLUSH_ZERO_ON</literal> (<literal>&lt;xmmintrin.h&gt;</literal>), 
  so technically it is available to users 
  of the Intel Intrinsics API.</para>

  <para>The VMX Vector facility provides a separate Vector Status and Control 
  register (VSCR) with a Non-Java Mode control bit. This control combines the 
  flush-to-zero semantics for floating point underflow and denormal values. But 
  this control only applies to VMX vector float instructions and does not apply 
  to VSX scalar floating Point or vector double instructions. The FPSCR does 
  define a Floating-Point non-IEEE mode which is optional in the architecture. 
  This would apply to Scalar and VSX floating-point operations if it were 
  implemented. This was largely intended for embedded processors and is not 
  implemented in the POWER processor line.</para>

  <para>As the flush-to-zero is primarily a performance enhancement and is 
  clearly outside the IEEE-754 standard, it may be best to simply ignore this 
  option for the intrinsic port.</para>

</section>

